<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<DIV8 N="4.89" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-38/section-4.89&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;38 CFR 4.89&quot;}">
<HEAD>รยง 4.89 Ratings for inactive nonpulmonary tuberculosis in effect on August 19, 1968.</HEAD>
<P>Public Law 90-493 repealed section 356 of title 38, United States Code which provided graduated ratings for inactive tuberculosis. The repealed section, however, still applies to the case of any veteran who on August 19, 1968, was receiving or entitled to receive compensation for tuberculosis. The use of the protective provisions of Pub. L. 90-493 should be mentioned in the discussion portion of all ratings in which these provisions are applied. For use in rating cases in which the protective provisions of Pub. L. 90-493 apply, the former evaluations are retained in this section.</P>
<DIV width="100%"><DIV class="gpotbl_div"><TABLE border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" class="gpotbl_table" frame="void" width="100%"><TR><TH class="gpotbl_colhed" scope="col">
</TH><TH class="gpotbl_colhed" scope="col">Rating
</TH></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">For 2 years after date of inactivity, following active tuberculosis, which was clinically identified during service or subsequently</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell">100
</TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">Thereafter, for 4 years, or in any event, to 6 years after date of inactivity</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell">50
</TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">Thereafter, for 5 years, or to 11 years after date of inactivity</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell">30
</TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">Thereafter, in the absence of a schedular compensable permanent residual</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell">0
</TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">Following the total rating for the 2-year period after date of inactivity, the schedular evaluation for residuals of nonpulmonary tuberculosis, <E T="03">i.e.</E>, ankylosis, surgical removal of a part, etc., if in excess of 50 percent or 30 percent will be assigned under the appropriate diagnostic code for the specific residual preceded by the diagnostic code for tuberculosis of the body part affected. For example, tuberculosis of the hipjoint with residual ankylosis would be coded 5001-5250.
</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell"></TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">The graduated ratings for nonpulmonary tuberculosis will not be combined with residuals of nonpulmonary tuberculosis unless the graduated rating and the rating for residual disability cover separate functional losses, e.g., graduated ratings for tuberculosis of the kidney and residuals of tuberculosis of the spine. Where there are existing pulmonary and nonpulmonary conditions, the graduated evaluation for the pulmonary, or for the nonpulmonary, condition will be utilized, combined with evaluations for residuals of the condition not covered by the graduated evaluation utilized, so as to provide the higher evaluation over such period.
</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell"></TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">The ending dates of all graduated ratings of nonpulmonary tuberculosis will be controlled by the date of attainment of inactivity.
</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell"></TD></TR><TR><TD align="left" class="gpotbl_cell" scope="row">These ratings are applicable only to veterans with nonpulmonary tuberculosis active on or after October 10, 1949.</TD><TD align="right" class="gpotbl_cell"></TD></TR></TABLE></DIV></DIV>
<CITA TYPE="N">[29 FR 6718, May 22, 1964, as amended at 34 FR 5062, Mar. 11, 1969; 43 FR 45361, Oct. 2, 1978]
</CITA>
</DIV8>
