<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<DIV8 N="4.76" TYPE="SECTION" hierarchy_metadata="{&quot;path&quot;:&quot;/on/_SUBSTITUTE_DATE_/title-38/section-4.76&quot;,&quot;citation&quot;:&quot;38 CFR 4.76&quot;}">
<HEAD>รยง 4.76 Visual acuity.</HEAD>
<P>(a) <I>Examination of visual acuity.</I> Examination of visual acuity must include the central <I>uncorrected</I> and <I>corrected</I> visual acuity for <I>distance</I> and <I>near</I> vision using Snellen's test type or its equivalent.</P>
<P>(b) <I>Evaluation of visual acuity.</I> (1) Evaluate central visual acuity on the basis of corrected distance vision with central fixation, even if a central scotoma is present. However, when the lens required to correct distance vision in the poorer eye differs by more than three diopters from the lens required to correct distance vision in the better eye (and the difference is not due to congenital or developmental refractive error), and either the poorer eye or both eyes are service connected, evaluate the visual acuity of the poorer eye using either its uncorrected or corrected visual acuity, whichever results in better combined visual acuity.</P>
<P>(2) Provided that he or she customarily wears contact lenses, evaluate the visual acuity of any individual affected by a corneal disorder that results in severe irregular astigmatism that can be improved more by contact lenses than by eyeglass lenses, as corrected by contact lenses.</P>
<P>(3) In any case where the examiner reports that there is a difference equal to two or more scheduled steps between near and distance corrected vision, with the near vision being worse, the examination report must include at least two recordings of near and distance corrected vision and an explanation of the reason for the difference. In these cases, evaluate based on corrected distance vision adjusted to one step poorer than measured.</P>
<P>(4) To evaluate the impairment of visual acuity where a claimant has a reported visual acuity that is between two sequentially listed visual acuities, use the visual acuity which permits the higher evaluation.</P>
<SECAUTH TYPE="N">(Authority: 38 U.S.C. 1155)
</SECAUTH>
<CITA TYPE="N">[73 FR 66549, Nov. 10, 2008]
</CITA>
</DIV8>
